<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!--
// *******************************************************************************
// * Copyright (C)2013, 2014, International Business Machines Corporation and *
// * others. All Rights Reserved. *
// *******************************************************************************
-->
<operatorModel
  xmlns="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/operator" 
  xmlns:cmn="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/common" 
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/operator operatorModel.xsd">
  <javaOperatorModel>
    <context> 
      <description docHref="doc/${nl}/spldoc/html/tk$com.ibm.streamsx.messaging/op$com.ibm.streamsx.messaging.jms$JMSSource.html">
The `JMSSource` operator reads data from a WebSphere MQ or an Apache Active MQ queue
or a topic and creates tuples from the read data. 

The `JMSSource` operator converts each WebSphere MQ or Apache Active MQ message to a separate tuple
and sends it to the output stream. A single message is converted into a single tuple.

# Behavior in a consistent region

The `JMSSource` operator is not supported in a consistent region.

# Exceptions

The following types of exceptions can occur:
 * Run time errors that halt the operator execution.
   * The JMSSource operator throws an exception and terminates in the following cases.
     For some exceptions, the trace and log information is logged in the console logs
     and also output to the optional output port if the application is configured to use the optional port.
     * During the initial connection attempt or during transient reconnection failures,
       if the **reconnectionPolicy** is set to `NoRetry` and the operator does not have a successful connection,
       or the **reconnectionPolicy** is set to `BoundedRetry` and the operator does not have a successful connection
       after the number of attempts that are specified in the **reconnectionBound** parameter. Successive data is lost.
     * The queue name is unknown.
     * The queue manager name is unknown.
     * The operator is unable to connect to the host or the port.
     * A MapMessage, StreamMessage, or BytesMessage does not contain the attributes that are specified in the native schema.
     * A MapMessage or StreamMessage contains attributes whose data type does not match the data type
       that is specified in the native schema and the conversion fails.
     * The message_class attribute in the access specification is bytes, stream, or map, and the name
       and type attributes of the &lt;native_schema&gt; element do not match the name and type attribute in the output stream schema.
     * When the message_class attribute is bytes and in the &lt;native_schema&gt; element,
       the type attribute is string or bytes and the length attribute is missing.
     * An invalid value is specified for the message_class attribute of the access specification.
     * If an attribute occurs more than once in the &lt;native_schema&gt; element.
     * The **connectionsDocument** parameter refers to an file that does not exist.
     * The **connectionsDocument** parameter is not specified and the `connections.xml` file is not present in the default location.
 * Run time errors that cause a message to be dropped and an error message to be logged.
   * The `JMSSource` operator throws an exception and discards the message in the following cases.
     The trace and log information for these exceptions is logged in the console logs
     and also output to the optional output port if the application is configured to use the optional port.
     * The `JMSSource` operator reads a message that does not match the message class in the &lt;native_schema&gt; element.
     * When a negative length (-2 or -4) is specified in the native schema for bytes and string data types
       and the message class is bytes, the operator expects the JMS message to start with a 2 or 4-byte length field.
       If there are insufficient bytes remaining in the JMS message,
       the operator discards the entire message and logs a run time error.
     * When a non-negative length is specified in the native schema for bytes and string,
       the operator attempts to read exactly that number of bytes from the BytesMessage.
       If there are insufficient bytes remaining in the JMS message,
       the operator discards the entire message and logs a run time error.
     * The **reconnectionBound** parameter is specified, but the **reconnectionPolicy** parameter is set
       to a value other than `BoundedRetry`.
 * Compile time errors.
   * The `JMSSource` operator throws a compile time error in the following cases.
     The trace and log information for these exceptions is logged in the console logs
     and also output to the optional output port if the application is configured to use the optional port.
     * The mandatory parameters, **connection** and **access** are not specified.
     * The **period** parameter is specified but the **reconnectionPolicy** parameter is not specified.
     * The **reconnectionBound** parameter is specified, but the **reconnectionPolicy** parameter is not specified.
     * The environment variables **STREAMS_MESSAGING_WMQ_HOME** and **STREAMS_MESSAGING_AMQ_HOME** are not set
       to the locations where the WMQ and AMQ libraries are installed.

+ Examples

This example shows the use of multiple `JMSSource` operators with different parameter combinations.

	composite Main {
	graph
	// JMSSource operator with the default etc/connections.xml(relative to the application directory)
	// connections document
	stream &lt;int32 id, rstring fname, rstring lname&gt;
	MyPersonNamesStream  = JMSSource()
	{
		param
			connection : "amqConn";
			access     : "amqAccess";
	}
	
	// JMSSource operator with fully qualified name of connections.xml
	stream &lt;int32 id, rstring fname, rstring lname&gt;
	MyPersonNamesStream = JMSSource()
	{
		param
			connectionDocument :"/home/streamsuser/connections/JMSconnections.xml";
			connection         : "amqConn"; 		
			access             : "amqAccess";
	}
	
	// JMSSource operator with optional output error port specified
	(stream &lt;int32 id, rstring fname, rstring lname&gt; MyPersonNamesStream ;
	stream &lt;rstring errorMessage&gt; ErrorStream) = JMSSource()
	{
		param
			connection : "amqConn";
			access     : "amqAccess";
	}
	
	// JMSSource operator with optional initDelay and reconnectionPolicy specified
	stream &lt;int32 id, rstring fname, rstring lname&gt;
	MyPersonNamesStream = JMSSource()
	{
		param
			connection         : "amqConn";
			access             : "amqAccess";
			reconnectionPolicy : "NoRetry";
			initDelay          : 10;
	}
	
	// JMSSource Operator with optional period and reconnectionPolicy specified
	stream &lt;int32 id, rstring fname, rstring lname&gt;
	MyPersonNamesStream = JMSSource()
	{
		param
		connection         : "amqConn";
		access             : "amqAccess";
		reconnectionPolicy : "InfiniteRetry";
		period             : 1.20;
	}
	
	// JMSSource operator with reconnectionPolicy specified as BoundedRetry
	stream &lt;int32 id, rstring fname, rstring lname&gt;
	MyPersonNamesStream = JMSSource()
	{
		param
			connection         : "amqConn";
			access             : "amqAccess";
			reconnectionPolicy : "BoundedRetry";
			reconnectionBound : 2;
			period: 1.20;
	}
	}                                                                                           
</description>
  	  <iconUri size="16">JMSSource_16.gif</iconUri>
	  <iconUri size="32">JMSSource_32.gif</iconUri>
	  <metrics>
      	<metric>
          <name>nMessagesRead</name>
          <description docHref="">The number of messages that are read successfully from a queue or topic.</description>
          <kind>Counter</kind>
        </metric>
        <metric>
          <name>nMessagesDropped</name>
          <description docHref="">The number of messages that are dropped in the application.</description>
          <kind>Counter</kind>
        </metric>
        <metric>
          <name>nReconnectionAttempts</name>
          <description docHref="">The number of reconnection attempts that are made before a successful connection occurs.</description>
          <kind>Counter</kind>
        </metric>
      </metrics>
      <executionSettings>
        <className>com.ibm.streamsx.messaging.jms.JMSSource</className>
        <vmArgs/>
      </executionSettings>
      <libraryDependencies>
        <library>
          <cmn:description>Java operator class library</cmn:description>
          <cmn:managedLibrary>
            <cmn:libPath>../../impl/java/bin</cmn:libPath>
            <cmn:libPath>../../impl/lib/com.ibm.streamsx.messaging.jar</cmn:libPath>      
          </cmn:managedLibrary>
        </library>	    
      </libraryDependencies>
      <codeTemplates>
        <codeTemplate name="JMSSource">
          <description>Basic JMSSource template</description>
          <template>stream&lt;${streamType}&gt; ${streamName} = JMSSource()   {
	      param
            	connection : &quot;${ConnectionSpecificationName}&quot;;
                access : &quot;${AccessSpecificationName}&quot;;
          }</template>
        </codeTemplate>
      </codeTemplates>
    </context>  
    <parameters>
    <parameter>
        <name>codepage</name>
        <description>
This optional parameter specifies the code page of the target system that is used to convert ustring for a Bytes message type.
If this parameter is specified, it must have exactly one value, which is a String constant.
If the parameter is not specified, the operator uses the default value of UTF8. </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <type>rstring</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
	  <parameter>
        <name>reconnectionPolicy</name>
        <description>
This is an optional parameter that specifies the reconnection policy.
The valid values are `NoRetry`, `InfiniteRetry`, and `BoundedRetry`.
If the parameter is not specified, the reconnection policy is set to `BoundedRetry` with a **reconnectionBound** of `5`
and a **period** of 60 seconds.</description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <type>rstring</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>reconnectionBound</name>
        <description>
This optional parameter specifies the number of successive connections that are attempted for an operator.
You can use this parameter only when the **reconnectionPolicy** parameter is specified and set to `BoundedRetry`,
otherwise a run time error occurs. If the **reconnectionBound** parameter is specified
and the **reconnectionPolicy** parameter is not set, a compile time error occurs.
The default value for the **reconnectionBound** parameter is `5`.</description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <type>int32</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>period</name>
        <description>
This optional parameter specifies the time period in seconds the operator waits before it tries to reconnect.
You can use this parameter only when the **reconnectionPolicy** parameter is specified,
otherwise a compile time error occurs. The default value for the **period** parameter is `60`.</description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <type>float64</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>initDelay</name>
        <description>
This optional parameter specifies the number of seconds that the `JMSSource` operator delays before it starts to produce tuples.
During the delay, the operator is blocked.</description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <type>int64</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>access</name>
        <description>
This mandatory parameter identifies the access specification name.</description>
        <optional>false</optional>
        <type>rstring</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>connection</name>
        <description>
This mandatory parameter identifies the name of the connection specification that contains an JMS element.</description>
        <optional>false</optional>
        <type>rstring</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
	  <parameter>
	  <name>connectionDocument</name>
        <description>
This optional parameter specifies the path name of the file that contains the connection and access specifications,
which are identified by the **connection** and **access** parameters.
If this parameter is not specified, the operator uses the file that is in the default location `./etc/connections.xml`.</description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <type>rstring</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
    </parameters>
    <inputPorts>
    </inputPorts>
    <outputPorts>
	  <outputPortSet>
        <description>
The `JMSSource` operator has one mandatory output and one optional output port.
If only the mandatory output port is specified, the operator submits a tuple for each message
that is successfully read from the messaging provider.
The mandatory output port is mutating and its punctuation mode is Free.</description>
        <windowPunctuationOutputMode>Free</windowPunctuationOutputMode>
        <windowPunctuationInputPort>-1</windowPunctuationInputPort>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
        <optional>false</optional>
      </outputPortSet>
      <outputPortSet>
        <description>
The `JMSSource` operator has one optional output port, which submits tuples when an error occurs.
		
If both optional and mandatory output ports are specified, the operator submits a tuple to the mandatory port
for each message that is read successfully and a tuple to the optional port if an error occurs when reading a message.
The tuple submitted to the optional port contains an error message for each message that could not be read successfully.
The optional output port has a single attribute of type rstring that contains this error message.
The optional output port is mutating and its punctuation mode is Free.</description>
        <windowPunctuationOutputMode>Free</windowPunctuationOutputMode>
        <windowPunctuationInputPort>-1</windowPunctuationInputPort>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
        <optional>true</optional>
      </outputPortSet>
    </outputPorts>
  </javaOperatorModel>
</operatorModel>

